Why stop making sense? Why a movie? Why a big suit? Where do the
odd movements come from? What will the band do next?
Stop Making Sense is a documentary, music film directed by Jonathan Demme.
A concert film documenting Talking Heads at the height of their popularity, on tour for their 1983 album "Speaking in Tongues." The band takes the stage one by
one and is joined by a cadre of guest musicians for a career-spanning and cinematic performance that features creative choreography and visuals.
Self - Vocals, Guitar, played by David Byrne.
Self - Drums, Vocals, played by Chris Frantz.
Self - Guitar, Keyboards, Vocals, played by Jerry Harrison.
Self - Bass, Percussion, Vocals, played by Tina Weymouth.
Self - Backing Vocals, played by Ednah Holt.
Self - Backing Vocals, played by Lynn Mabry.
Stop Making Sense is a 1984 American concert film featuring a live
performance by the American rock band Talking Heads.
The film was directed by Jonathan Demme and executive produced
by Gary Kurfirst, the band’s longtime manager.
The film was shot over four nights in December 1983 at Hollywood’s Pantages Theatre while
Talking Heads were on tour promoting their 1983 album, Speaking in Tongues.
Stop Making Sense includes performances of the early Talking Heads single, "Psycho Killer"
(1977), through to their most recent hit at the time, "Burning Down the House" (1983).
It also includes songs from the solo career of frontman David Byrne and by Tom Tom
Club, the side project of drummer Chris Frantz and bassist Tina Weymouth.
The film was independently produced and the band raised
the budget of $1.2 million themselves.
The four core members of Talking Heads are joined by backing singers Lynn Mabry and Ednah Holt,
guitarist Alex Weir, keyboardist Bernie Worrell and percussionist Steve Scales.
Stop Making Sense is considered by many critics to be a classic
and one of the greatest concert films of all time.
The film is a pioneering example of the use of early digital audio techniques.
In 2021, it was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of Congress as being "culturally,
historically, or aesthetically significant." A special 4K restoration of the film was re-released in theaters in September 2023 by A24.
The film explores themes of concert, rock band,
concert film, post-punk, new wave.